Tufts Published Scholarship PB
Tufts Archival Research Center
- Tufts Published Scholarship, 2008 -- 2014; 1983 -- 2014; PB.002; 26 Digital Object(s)
  - Overcoming natural replication barriers: differential helicase requirements, 2011; PB.002.00010; Freudenreich, Catherine H.; Anand, Ranjith P.; Shah, Kartik A.; Niu, Hengyao; Sung, Patrick; Mirkin, Sergei M.
    DNA sequences that form secondary structures or bind protein complexes are known barriers to replication and potential inducers of genome instability. In order to determine which helicases facilitate DNA replication across these barriers, we analyzed fork progression through them in wild-type and mutant yeast cells, using 2-dimensional gel-electrophoretic analysis of the replication intermediates. We show that the Srs2 protein facilitates replication of hairpin-forming CGG/CCG repeats and prevents chromosome fragility at the repeat, whereas it does not affect replication of G-quadruplex forming sequences or a protein-bound repeat. Srs2 helicase activity is required for hairpin unwinding and fork progression. Also, the PCNA binding domain of Srs2 is required for its in vivo role of replication through hairpins. In contrast, the absence of Sgs1 or Pif1 helicases did not inhibit replication through structural barriers, though Pif1 did facilitate replication of a telomeric protein barrier. Interestingly, replication through a protein barrier but not a DNA structure barrier was modulated by nucleotide pool levels, illuminating a different mechanism by which cells can regulate fork progression through protein-mediated stall sites. Our analyses reveal fundamental differences in the replication of DNA structural versus protein barriers, with Srs2 helicase activity exclusively required for fork progression through hairpin structures.
    DNA replication; Department of Biology
  - Parametric level set reconstruction methods for hyperspectral diffuse optical tomography, 2012; PB.002.00011; Larusson, Fridrik; Fantini, Sergio; Miller, Eric L.; A parametric level set method (PaLS) is implemented for image reconstruction for hyperspectral diffuse optical tomography (DOT). Chromophore concentrations and diffusion amplitude are recovered using a linearized Born approximation model and employing data from over 100 wavelengths. The images to be recovered are taken to be piecewise constant and a newly introduced, shape-based model is used as the foundation for reconstruction. The PaLS method significantly reduces the number of unknowns relative to more traditional level-set reconstruction methods and has been show to be particularly well suited for ill-posed inverse problems such as the one of interest here. We report on reconstructions for multiple chromophores from simulated and experimental data where the PaLS method provides a more accurate estimation of chromophore concentrations compared to a pixel-based method.
    Department of Biomedical Engineering; Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering
  - Competition between Replicative and Translesion Polymerases during Homologous Recombination Repair in Drosophila, 2012; PB.002.00012; McVey, Mitch; Kane, Daniel P.; Shusterman, Michael
    Department of Biology; Tufts Sackler School of Graduate Biomedical Sciences. Program in Genetics
  - Structure, photophysics, and photooxidation of crowded diethynyltetracenes, 2012; PB.002.00013; Zhang, Jingjing; Sarrafpour, Syena; Haas, Terry E.; Thomas, Samuel W. III; This paper describes a previously unreported class of sterically crowded tetracene derivatives that have both phenyl and ethynyl substituents. The steric crowding above and below the tetracene core prevents overlap between the extended p-systems of the acenes. Substituent effects cause these tetra-substituted tetracenes to have absorbance and fluorescence spectra red shifted from either disubstituted derivatives or rubrenes, such that they have spectra similar to diarylpentacenes, but with higher quantum yields of fluorescence and greater photostability. These new molecules also undergo cycloaddition reactions with 1O2, giving regioisomeric mixtures of endoperoxides, and in contrast to longer acenes, the ethynyl substituents show only a modest stabilizing effect to photooxidation. Ethynylated tetracenes also exhibited photochromism, with their endoperoxides undergoing cycloreversion to yield the acene starting material at room temperature in the dark.
    Department of Chemistry
  - A qualitative study of leadership characteristics among women who catalyze positive community change, 2012; PB.002.00014; Folta, Sara C.; Nelson, Miriam; Ackerman, Jennifer
    John Hancock Research Center on Physical Activity, Nutrition, and Obesity Prevention; Jonathan M. Tisch College of Citizenship and Public Service
  - Evaluating resource sharing performance in an academic health sciences library utilizing the RapidILL System, 2009; PB.002.00015; Rabinowitz, Judy; To stay in line with user needs and workflow demands, interlibrary loan officers must continuously incorporate innovative technologies into their departments. Evaluating the usefulness of these new systems to ensure appropriate implementation, can be a large undertaking as there are many issues to address during such an assessment. This study tracked the interlibrary loan activity from June through November of 2005, 2007, and 2008 of Tufts University Hirsh Health Sciences Library, in order to explore the advantages and disadvantages of participating in the RapidILL resource sharing system. Volume changes, breadth of resource sharing circles, transactional fees, staffing needs, turnaround time, and fill rate, were the main facets of interlibrary loan borrowing and lending activity analyzed.
    Interlibrary loans; Document delivery; Hirsch Health Sciences Library; Boston Library Consortium
  - Age-Dependent Changes in the Sphingolipid Composition of Mouse CD4+ T Cell Membranes and Immune Synapses Implicate Glucosylceramides in Age- Related T Cell Dysfunction, 2012-10; PB.002.00016; Molano, Alberto; Huang, Zhaofeng; Marko, Melissa G.; Azzi, Angelo; Wu, Dayong; Bunnell, Stephen C.; Meydani, Simin Nikbin; To determine whether changes in sphingolipid composition are associated with age-related immune dysfunction, we analyzed the core sphingolipidome (i.e., all of the metabolites through the first headgroup additions) of young and aged CD4+ T cells. Since sphingolipids influence the biophysical properties of membranes, we evaluated the compositions of immune synapse (IS) and non-IS fractions prepared by magnetic immuno-isolation. Broadly, increased amounts of sphingomyelins, dihydrosphingomyelins and ceramides were found in aged CD4+ T cells. After normalizing for total sphingolipid content, a statistically significant decrease in the molar fraction of glucosylceramides was evident in both the non-IS and IS fractions of aged T cells. This change was balanced by less dramatic increases in the molar fractions of sphingomyelins and dihydrosphingomyelins in aged CD4+ T cells. In vitro, the direct or enzymatic enhancement of ceramide levels decreased CD4+ T cell proliferation without regard for the age of the responding T cells. In contrast, the in vitro inhibition of glucosylceramidase preferentially increased the proliferation of aged CD4+ T cells. These results suggest that reductions in glucosylceramide abundance contribute to age-related impairments in CD4+ T cell function.
    Provost Open Access Fund; Jean Mayer USDA Human Nutrition Research Center on Aging; Sackler Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences. Department of Pathology
  - Female Goldeneye Ducks (Bucephala clangula) Do Not Discriminate among Male Precopulatory Display Patterns, 2013-03; PB.002.00017; Dane, Benjamin; Harris, Rebecca; Reed, J. Michael; Female goldeneyes remain motionless on the surface of the water while single males circle them performing a series of highly stereotyped displays. After performing between eight and 90 of these displays the male either copulates or attempts to copulate with the female. However, females allow only 58% of males to mount them, while rejecting 42%. We have examined 804 of these precopulatory sequences containing 11,841 actions in an effort to determine why females find some display sequences of males unsuitable, while others are accepted. Males have an extraordinarily varied sequence of actions, and sequence variation leading to successful and unsuccessful copulation attempts was similar. Most surprising was the tendency of males to eliminate one of the five actions, whether in successful or unsuccessful attempts. As unlikely as we think it might be as the result of natural selection, the only statistically significant difference we found between successful and unsuccessful attempts was the reduction in the frequency of expression of one or more of the behaviors in successful attempts. These observations, coupled with the large variation seen in most sequences, suggest that there is not a correct sequence, or even a correct set of actions leading to copulation. The male must, however, perform goldeneye species- specific precopulatory behavior as performed by adult males, although it apparently can be performed in a wide variety of patterns.
    Provost Open Access Fund; Department of Biology
  - Improved Fourier-based characterization of intracellular fractal features, 2012-09; PB.002.00018; Xylas, Joanna; Quinn, Kyle P.; Hunter, Martin; Georgakoudi, Irene; A novel Fourier-based image analysis method for measuring fractal features is presented which can significantly reduce artifacts due to non-fractal edge effects. The technique is broadly applicable to the quantitative characterization of internal morphology (texture) of image features with well-defined borders. In this study, we explore the capacity of this method for quantitative assessment of intracellular fractal morphology of mitochondrial networks in images of normal and diseased (precancerous) epithelial tissues. Using a combination of simulated fractal images and endogenous two-photon excited fluorescence (TPEF) microscopy, our method is shown to more accurately characterize the exponent of the high- frequency power spectral density (PSD) of these images in the presence of artifacts that arise due to cellular and nuclear borders.
    Provost Open Access Fund; Department of Biomedical Engineering
  - Effective Control of Schistosoma haematobium Infection in a Ghanaian Community following Installation of a Water Recreation Area, 2012-07; PB.002.00019; Kosinski, Karen C.; Durant, John L.; Stadecker, Miguel J.; Woodin, Mark; Gute, David M.; Background: Urogenital schistosomiasis caused by Schistosoma haematobium was endemic in Adasawase, Ghana in 2007. Transmission was reported to be primarily through recreational water contact. Methods: We designed a water recreation area (WRA) to prevent transmission to school-aged children. The WRA features a concrete pool supplied by a borehole well and a gravity-driven rainwater collection system; it is 30 m2 and is split into shallow and deep sections to accommodate a variety of age groups. The WRA opened in 2009 and children were encouraged to use it for recreation as opposed to the local river. We screened children annually for S. haematobium eggs in their urine in 2008, 2009, and 2010 and established differences in infection rates before (2008-09) and after (2009-10) installation of the WRA. After each annual screening, children were treated with praziquantel and rescreened to confirm parasite clearance. Principal Findings: Initial baseline testing in 2008 established that 105 of 247 (42.5%) children were egg-positive. In 2009, with drug treatment alone, the pre-WRA annual cumulative incidence of infection was 29 of 216 (13.4%). In 2010, this incidence rate fell significantly (p,0.001, chi-squared) to 9 of 245 (3.7%) children after installation of the WRA. Logistic regression analysis was used to determine correlates of infection among the variables age, sex, distance between home and river, minutes observed at the river, low height-for-age, low weight-for-age, low Body Mass Index (BMI)-for-age, and previous infection status. Conclusion/Significance: The installation and use of a WRA is a feasible and highly effective means to reduce the incidence of schistosomiasis in school-aged children in a rural Ghanaian community. In conjunction with drug treatment and education, such an intervention can represent a significant step towards the control of schistosomiasis. The WRA should be tested in other water-rich endemic areas to determine whether infection prevalence can be substantially reduced.
    Provost Open Access Fund; Tufts University. Community Health Program; Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering; Sackler Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences. Department of Pathology
  - HDAC Activity Is Required during Xenopus Tail Regeneration, 2011-10; PB.002.00020; Tseng. Ai-Sun; Lemire, Joan M.; Levin, Michael; The ability to fully restore damaged or lost organs is present in only a subset of animals. The Xenopus tadpole tail is a complex appendage, containing epidermis, muscle, nerves, spinal cord, and vasculature, which regenerates after amputation. Understanding the mechanisms of tail regeneration may lead to new insights to promote biomedical regeneration in non-regenerative tissues. Although chromatin remodeling is known to be critical for stem cell pluripotency, its role in complex organ regeneration in vivo remains largely uncharacterized. Here we show that histone deacetylase (HDAC) activity is required for the early stages of tail regeneration. HDAC1 is expressed during the 1st two days of regeneration. Pharmacological blockade of HDACs using Trichostatin A (TSA) increased histone acetylation levels in the amputated tail. Furthermore, treatment with TSA or another HDAC inhibitor, valproic acid, specifically inhibited regeneration. Over-expression of wild-type Mad3, a transcriptional repressor known to associate in a complex with HDACs via Sin3, inhibited regeneration. Similarly, expression of a Mad3 mutant lacking the Sin3-interacting domain that is required for HDAC binding also blocks regeneration, suggesting that HDAC and Mad3 may act together to regulate regeneration. Inhibition of HDAC function resulted in aberrant expression of Notch1 and BMP2, two genes known to be required for tail regeneration. Our results identify a novel early role for HDAC in appendage regeneration and suggest that modulation of histone acetylation is important in regenerative repair of complex appendages.
    Provost Open Access Fund; Tufts Center for Regenerative and Developmental Biology. Department of Developmental Biology
  - Diminished rostral anterior cingulate cortex activation during trauma-unrelated emotional interference in PTSD, 2013; PB.002.00021; Offringa, Reid; Brohawn, Kathryn Handwerger; Staples, Lindsay K.; Dubois,Stacey J.; Pfaff, Danielle L.; VanElzakker, Michael B.; Davis, F Caroline; Shin, Lisa M.; Background: Previous research suggests that individuals with posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) preferentially attend to trauma-related emotional stimuli and have difficulty completing unrelated concurrent tasks. Compared to trauma-exposed control groups, individuals with PTSD also exhibit lower rostral anterior cingulate cortex (rACC) activation during tasks involving interference from trauma-related stimuli. However, it is not clear whether relatively diminished rACC activation in PTSD also occurs during interference tasks involving trauma-unrelated emotional stimuli. The present study employed functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) and an interference task that involves emotional facial expressions and elicits rACC activation in healthy participants. Findings: While performing a trauma-unrelated emotional interference task, participants with PTSD (n=17) showed less rACC activation than trauma-exposed non-PTSD (TENP; n=18) participants. In the PTSD group, rACC activation was negatively correlated with the severity of re-experiencing symptoms. The two groups did not significantly differ on behavioral measures (i.e., response times and error rates). Conclusions: These findings suggest that relatively diminished rACC activation in PTSD can be observed in interference tasks involving trauma-unrelated emotional stimuli, indicating a more general functional brain abnormality in this disorder. Future neuroimaging studies need not employ trauma-related stimuli in order to detect rACC abnormalities in PTSD.
    Provost Open Access Fund; Department of Psychology
  - P. T. Barnum, Jumbo the Elephant, and the Barnum Museum of Natural History at Tufts University, 2012; PB.002.00022; McClellan, Andrew; In 1883, the great showman P. T. Barnum agreed to build an eponymous museum of natural history on the campus of Tufts University, which he had served as a founding trustee. After a long career managing dime museums and a travelling circus, Barnum hoped to secure a positive legacy through the creation of an unambiguously serious institution. In addition to building and collections funds, Barnum supplied the Tufts museum – as well as the Smithsonian and American Museum of Natural History in New York – with exotic and valuable dead animals from his circus. Barnum brought his influence to bear on the latter two in order to develop his museum at Tufts. His greatest prize was Jumbo the Elephant, whose skin and bones were involved in a contentious tug-of-war among the three museums following his death in a train accident in 1885.
    Barnum Museum of Natural History; Natural history museum trustees; Barnum, P. T. (Phineas Taylor); Capen, Elmer Hewitt
  - Forging New Service Paths: Institutional Approaches to Providing Research Data Management Services, 2014; PB.002.00023; Raboin, Regina F.; Reznik-Zellen, Rebecca.; Salo, Dorothea.; This paper describes three different institutional experiences in developing research data management programs and services, challenges/opportunities and lessons learned.This paper is based on the Librarian Panel Discussion during the 4th Annual University of Massachusetts and New England Region e-Science Symposium. Librarians representing large public and private research universities presented an overview of service models developed at their respective organizations to bring support for data management and eScience to their communities. The approaches described include two library-based, integrated service models and one collaboratively-staffed, center-based service model.
    Research--Information services.; Institutional repositories.; Communication in learning and scholarship -- Technological innovations.; Electronic information resources -- Management.; Libraries and scholars.
  - Documenting the American Military Experience in the Iraq and Afghanistan Wars, 2014; PB.002.00024; Wilczek, Eliot; Soyka, Heather; This essay reviews the challenges of documenting the American military experience in the Iraq and Afghanistan wars. It looks at the appraisal challenges presented by the complexities of counterinsurgency warfare. It then examines the nature of current military records with a focus on their volume and mix of structured and informal documents and data. Finally, it reviews the recordkeeping challenges faced by the military during these two wars. This essay addresses issues of broad archival concern beyond just military records: documenting complex activities and events, appraising big data and informal data, and effectively managing active records.
    Iraq War, 2003-2011; Appraisal of archival materials.; Records--Management.; Afghan War, 2001-.; United States. Army--Records and correspondence.
  - One Health Core Competency Domains, Subdomains, and Competency Examples, 2014; PB.002.00025; Lee, Mary Y.
    This document is a product of the Global One Health Core Competencies (OHCC) Working Group as part of the global RESPOND Initiative, USAID Emerging Pandemic Threats Program. The purpose of this document is to summarize the Global OHCC Working Group's guiding framework for OHCC curriculum mapping, curriculum development, and other faculty or staff development and training activities that can be customized to an audience's needs, regardless of sector.Contents of this document include: 1) definitions and comments on key terms used in the document, 2) a 2-page Overview that can be used as an introduction for potential audiences, 3) the seven Global Working Group OHCC Domains and corresponding examples of Subdomains and Sample Competencies that support effective One Health approaches, and 4) the Global OHCC Working Group member list.
    United States.--Agency for International Development.
  - Lead & Lead Poisoning in Antiquity, 1983; PB.002.00026; Nriagu, Jerome O.; 318 Megabytes
    Antiquities; Lead; Lead poisoning